Guide to the Stanford University, School of Earth Sciences, Oral History Interviews
Stanford University Libraries
Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, School of Earth Sciences, oral history interviews
1983-1999
SC4-0900 EARTH
Stanford University. School of Earth Sciences
0.5 Linear feet
Transcripts and audio tapes of interviews with Stanford faculty and former students.
Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives Stanford University Libraries 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: speccollref@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://www-sul.stanford.edu/depts/spc/spc.html
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, 2000.
Information about Access
None.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
Interviews conducted with professors and former students in the School of Earth Sciences: Robert G. Coleman, William R. Dickinson, John W. Harbaugh, James C. Ingle, A. Myra Keen, Mary Balch Kennedy, Konrad Krauskopf, Ronald J. P. Lyon, Edgar A. McDowell, Frank G. Miller, Benjamin M. Page, and Russell A. Pomeroy. Participants discuss their original interest in geology, what brought them to Stanford, their subsequent careers, the Stanford curriculum, development of the School of Earth Sciences, and other concerns, including student life at Stanford.
Access Terms
Coleman, Robert G.; Compton, Robert R.; Dickinson, William R.; Harbaugh, John Warvelle, 1926-; Ingle James C.; Keen, A. Myra (Angeline Myra), 1905-; Kennedy, Mary Balch.; Krauskopf, Konrad Bates, 1910-; Lyon, R. J. P. (Ronald James Pearson), 1928-; McDowell, Edgar A.; Miller, Frank G.; Page, Benjamin M. (Benjamin Markham), 1911-; Pomeroy, Russell A.; Stanford University--Faculty.; Stanford University--History.; Stanford University--Students.; Geology.
Collection Contents
- Transcripts, 1983-1999
  - Bob Coleman and Russ Pomeroy; interviewed by Judy Terry Smith., October 29, 1996 (Box 1)
    Subjects include football, G.I. Bill, role of TA's, geology field work, asbestos, use of computers in geology, earthquakes, future of geological sciences, and Coleman's experiences teaching in Oman.
  - Robert R. Compton; interviewed by Janet Bauder Thornberg and Judy Terry Smith., October 13, 1999 (Box 1)
    Subjects include life at Stanford before and after World War II, his experiences in the Navy during World War II, living at Stanford Village after the war, the summer geology course and admitting women to it, geology curriculum especially the G-1 and G-2 classes, and the student strike of 1970.
  - John Harbaugh; interviewed by Keith Kvenvolden, Ben Page, and Judy Terry Smith., August 9, 1996 (Box 1)
    Subjects include history and development of the School of Earth Sciences, use of computers in geology, outside funding, university committee work, entrepreneurial activities, and alumni relations.
  - A. Myra Keen; interviewed in by Eugene V. Coan., September 1983 (Box 1)
    Subjects include field work collecting marine shells along Pacific Coast, trips to the Gulf of California (Bechtel groups), recollections of Ida S. Oldroyd and her husband Thomas S. Oldroyd, her graduate students, and other collectors (Tom Burch, John A. Burch, Rose Burch).
  - Mary Balch Kennedy; interviewed by Judy Terry Smith and Juliet R. Crider., July 25, 1997 (Box 1)
    Subjects include her student years at Mills College and Stanford, discrimination against women in the field of geology, her work history, friendship with Lucile Salter Packard, women's clubs, volunteering, and trips to Nepal in 1962 and Saudi Arabia in 1964.
  - Konnie Krauskopf; interviewed by Carol Ann Hodges, Judy Terry Smith, and Keith Kvenvolder., May 7, 1996 (Box 1)
    Subjects include his work with the USGS, World War II and post-war work, the School under Dean A. I. Leverson, relations with Provost Fred Terman, funding, environmental issues, nuclear waste, collegiality among faculty, and his GSA presidential address, ca. 1968.
  - Ron Lyon; interviewed by John Harbaugh, George Parks, and Judy Terry Smith., February 8, 2000 (Box 1)
    Subjects include his student experiences in Australia and at UC Berkeley, work life (Kennecott Research, SRI, NASA), remote sensing, lunar geology, mapping the Amazon Basin by radar, and the use of computers in geology.
  - Edgar A. McDowell; interviewed by Judy Terry Smith and John Harbaugh., July 26, 1999 (Box 1)
    Subjects include the San Juan Hill faculty housing area on campus, his father's career at Stanford, alumni relations, the Newsoms (John F. Newsom, John B. Newsom, and Margaret Nagel Newsom), Lewis Terman, student life at Stanford, football games, Herbert and Lou Henry Hoover, the 1928 presidential election night activities on campus, and his career with Southern Pacific Railroad.
  - Frank G. Miller, interviewed March 24, 1986. (Box 1)
    Subjects include his comments on Stanford faculty of the 1950s to 1970s, courses and field work in the petroleum engineering program, industry involvement, and curriculum for petroleum engineering.
  - Ben Page and William R. Dickinson; interviewed by Keith Kvenvolden, Judy Terry Smith, and Jackie Dickinson., April 16, 1996 (Box 1)
    Subjects include the summer geology course, Dickinson's memories of Page as a teacher, doing work on the San Andreas Fault, plate tectonics, other Stanford faculty, and their respective careers.
- Audio Tapes, 1983-1999; microcassettes except where noted (Box 2)
  - Coleman, Bob, 1996
  - Compton, Robert R., 1999
  - Harbaugh, John, 1996
  - Ingle, Jim, 1986
  - Kennedy, Mary Balch, 1997
  - Krauskopf, Konnie, 1996
  - Lyon, Ron
  - McDowell, Edgar A., 1999
  - Miller, Frank G., 1986
  - Miller & Ingle, 1986; regular audio cassette
  - Page, Ben & Dickinson, William R., 1996